A lot of people focus on the execution
which is on paper great. But I believe
the success of a test is at least 50%
dependent on how you plan it, how you
strategize it, how you hypothesize it,
and how you execute it. And execution is
just the what part. Maybe it's even
sometimes less than 50%. How you execute
matters more than you execute or not.
>> Hello, I'm your host David Bernard. My
guest today is Alpert Tanner, head of
performance marketing at a stealth mode
app studio, working on productivity and
utility apps. Alper has been in mobile
growth for over a decade, leading UA and
Martekch efforts across a wide range of
verticals and managing 8 figure annual
budgets. On the podcast, I talk with
Alper about the competitive advantage of
ignoring some best practices, the risk
of drawing false conclusions when
researching competitor ads, and why poor
metrics are just facts until proven
problematic. Hey, Alper, thanks so much
for joining me on the podcast today.
>> Yeah, thank you for having me.
>> So, it's been a long time coming. Uh you
and I first met in person at MAU years
ago and we've kind of talked off and on
about getting you on the podcast, but
recently we were talking about a lot of
your contrarian ideas just that you
think a little bit differently uh and
like to challenge the kind of rules of
thumb and I thought that would be an
especially fun thing to talk about and
so let let's kick it off with that. the
podcast shares a ton of like rules of
thumb and like hey try this don't try
that like oh this didn't work for me so
you probably shouldn't do it and you
know on the revenue cap blog we share
all sorts of of articles like that but
you went through as you and I have been
talking preparing for this episode and
you kind of ripped holes in in some of
the like rules of thumb so at a high
level why don't you just start off like
how do you think about these kind of
like best practices and rules of thumb
>> there are definitely best practices and
rules of thumb that you should stick I
don't know 80% of the time but that
doesn't mean they are universal for
every single case. So if I were the app
developer listening all these ideas of
dos and don'ts I would prioritize it
based on my current situation data and I
would still try them just to see that it
also doesn't work. Of course it has to
be reasonable but idea is that your data
should uh show you that instead of oh we
heard someone said XY Z type of an
approach. So I think this applies across
the way you test the creatives, the way
you test incrementality, the way you
test your bidding strategy. So I think
these are all meaningful tests to a
certain extent depending on what stage
you're in. If you don't have your own
learnings, of course, it's smarter to
leverage others learnings and it can
just help you to prioritize. If you hear
something didn't work for 20 people,
just dep prioritize it. But doesn't
mean, oh, forget about this because it's
not going to work for you because
algorithms are constantly changing and
improving. And whatever someone tried 6
months ago can work today. And then we
see that it's happening across multiple
platforms within the platforms as well
like the campaign a that or like
specific targeting that was working
really well stops working. This is like
a day-to-day thing or your creative dies
right like where the creative that
worked 6 months ago that you had to
relaunch it works great again. So also
it potentially looks much better now
because of the late conversions and
stuff. So it's not black and white. I
think when you hear such advice, you
should definitely like take them as
suggestions. But when it comes to
execution and prioritization, you should
do that based on your own data because
you don't know the history of that
particular account and why particular
thing didn't work. And there are several
or a lot of reasons why a particular
setup would work for one market or
platform versus not. And that's why they
are all individual cases. There are
definitely, as I said, best practices
that are universal, but I would always
challenge them. I take them as, okay,
great. Let me try it. [laughter]
>> Yeah.
>> Well, I I I think you've just created a
new rule of thumb. I I I like that that
you should spend 80% of your time on the
best practices and learn because like
you said, if 20 people tried it and it
failed, maybe it is going to fail for
you. But then take 20% of your energy,
your budget, your efforts and do the
exact opposite of the best practices
[laughter] and figure out for yourself
why why they learn. And and to your
point, like you know, if you're early
and you don't have a lot of resources,
you don't want to overindex on being a
contrarian. But I mean, that's the whole
thing, right? Is that there there's
alpha in the best practices and that's
why they're the best practices. But then
there's also alpha in the things people
aren't trying or the things that certain
people failed at, but you're going to
succeed in that for a very for something
that's very specific to your app or your
niche or your market or some other thing
like that. So yeah, the new rule of
thumb. [laughter]
Follow best practices 80% of the time
and try crazy stuff 20% of the time. I
like that. Let's go through some of
these like more specific contrarian
takes. And one of the ones we were
discussing is that sometimes you just
need to take something as a fact and not
consider it a problem until it becomes a
problem. And the example you gave me,
and I'd love for you to elaborate on
this, is that if your trial conversion
is low, and you're like, "Oh, trial
conversion being low is a problem."
Well, is it a problem? Like, are you
getting cheaper installs? Tell me about
that.
>> Yeah, like typically people would say
like, "Oh, we have, I don't know,
install to start trial ratio, I don't
know, 5%." And, you know, usual health
tier benchmark is more like 15 to 20%
and such. And I'm like, "Okay, what what
have you done? Like, what have you
tried?" and how did you interpret the
results? How did you build on those
results? They're like, "Oh, we didn't
because it's a problem." Uh, you know,
so that's not a it's just a fact. I
think something becomes a problem after
you systematically test it, iterate on
the results and try many different ways
from let's say radical to iterative and
you're still stuck at the same level,
then I think I can consider that as a
potential problem.
>> [clears throat]
>> Instead, you should always see what you
can do or understand the root cause. So,
diagnose any factual problem that you
consider as a problem and then come up
with an action plan and then measure the
results to see the impact. It's as easy
as that. It might sound very like
straightforward but I can tell you like
many people bypass uh this kind of
stepby-step funnel in figuring out stuff
because when you follow such an approach
you realize that oh actually it's not a
problem like or I don't know it's simple
as people say like oh we tried I don't
know snap and it didn't work. I'm like
okay how did you try it? Oh we spend I
don't know 5k in a week and it didn't
work. I'm like yeah that's not a problem
that snap didn't work. you just didn't
test the channel in a proper way that is
optimal for the for the channel. Uh you
shouldn't test a channel just for a
week. And same goes for I don't know
creatives to channels or the markets.
Oh, it's too expensive for this market
or that channel didn't work. So people
like to come to conclusions fast and I
think because of the priorities like
because of this scarcity kind of a
mindset like they want to reach
conclusions really fast and they want to
move on to the next. So when they are in
this kind of a mindset I think then
they're missing out on testing things
properly. Like I think a lot of people
focus on the execution which is on paper
great but I believe the success of a
test is at least 50% dependent on how
you plan it, how you strategize it, how
you hypothesize it and how you execute
it. And execution is just the what part.
Maybe it's even sometimes less than 50%.
But basically how you execute matters
more than you execute or not. Sometimes
people also say, "Oh, we tried, I don't
know, let's say look alike. It didn't
work." Because the way they tried look
alike was a 10% run it for a week,
that's it. No seed testing, no different
ranges of testing and such. You cannot
just call the whole thing doesn't work.
If you don't slice and dice and try like
different things. That's kind of my
approach and that's how I deal with
day-to-day business to understand and
prioritize it based on okay how can I
say I tested something and what
information I need to call the shots
that it doesn't work or it does work. So
this kind of thinking I think will force
you to think of all the preliminary
steps on what you should be considering
and so on. Yeah,
>> I like that kind of root cause thinking.
I actually did a talk at MAU a couple
years ago about the the top three
subscription app metrics um that really
matter. And that was kind of the thrust
of of my talk was that you need to look
at the whole funnel, not just individual
metrics. And and like what you were
saying, it's like if you have a low
trial conversion rate or if you have a
low install to trial rate or if you
overly focus on any one metric and
you're like, "Oh, this is a problem."
And you like grind and grind and grind
on that quote unquote problem when maybe
you can get like really cheap installs
and the really cheap installs are why
you have a low conversion. But hey,
that's not a problem. It's not a problem
when you get really cheap installs and
your conversion rate's not great. Like
that's maybe just a natural fact of your
business that for whatever reason you're
getting incredibly cheap installs and
and the example I always use with this
is like you know my apps have gotten
featured a ton by Apple over the years
and getting featured is fantastic
because it's totally free zero cost of
install but guess what those cohorts
convert really poorly. So do I have a
conversion problem? I don't know. I know
that those cohorts don't convert very
well, but like should I overly focus on
that or should I be more focused on top
of funnel and like finding other ways?
And so a great reminder to not get
overly focused on any one specific thing
to the exclusion of like all the
different moving parts in the funnel.
And I like the way you phrased it too,
like it's just a fact. That's a fact
right now. That's a fact. Is it a
problem? We don't know. It's a fact.
Figure out if it's a problem. Don't just
assume it's a problem.
>> Yeah.
>> So, another thing you mentioned you've
been thinking a lot about lately is
creative interpretation. And you know,
we had Eric Seford on the podcast
recently and he's intentionally a bit
provocative saying like, "Don't even
try. Don't even try to interpret the
creatives." But you were telling me like
you do think there are things that you
could learn from trying to interpret why
things won, why they didn't. So what is
your process for looking at the winning
creatives and like finding some value in
that process?
>> I think looking at the output of a
creative performance definitely matters
because that's how you will iterate and
find the next winners and or the losers.
It is important to look at the relative
metrics as well. So maybe what he's
referring to is more like don't take it
as your source of truth because platform
is doing the modeling and such but at
the end of the day the output slash the
performance of the creative matters and
the approach should be more like what
can we learn from it regardless of the
output in a way like good or bad it's
all about the learning okay this
creative for whatever reason performed
better and other creative performed
performed for whatever reason worse.
Let's understand why. What is the hook
rate? How is the thumbnail? What is the
audio? What is the background? And this
and that. So once we understand and then
we we start changing one variable at a
time, then it becomes a lot more clearer
on how we can engineer the success,
right? I mean that's the whole point of
that's how you create winners from the
winners because you have a winning
concept and thanks to the interpretation
of the output you're able to create more
winners because you look at the relative
metrics that's a guidance for what you
should be testing and what you should be
not testing anymore because whatever you
do in that particular case doesn't work
however I have seen from the same
concept cept like the third variation
worked but the first and second failed.
It's the same concept. It's just
slightly different messaging and such.
So that's why you would always test with
few variations just to avoid such cases
where where you don't just jump to
conclusion of a whole concept and so on.
I think that's also important. So there
could be of course false positives and
so on like you know nothing is perfect
but also I'm not also saying like oh you
should trust algorithm blindly and and
stuff like that. What I'm just saying is
like we should be able to interpret the
results and then drive conclusions to
shape the next creative iterations based
on that. So that's when you need to
interpret the output and then what
matters at the end of the day is your
success rate and not the amount of
creatives because I think LinkedIn
nowadays is full of oh you know what we
just tested 500 creatives oh no we
tested 700 how much did you test kind of
race uh that is not so meaningful
because those numbers alone don't matter
if your success rate is very low I would
more look at your cost per successful
creative that is beating the BAU ads
performance. And it doesn't matter if
you test 20 versus 200. Of course, okay,
20 versus 200 might matter, but it
doesn't matter if you're testing a very
high amount of creatives with a little
success. It matters more. You test less
amount of creatives, stronger
hypothesis, stronger investment from an
analyzing and hypothesizing way with a
higher success rate. That what matters
more than just the total number of
creatives that you're testing. I see
potential issues when the creative
amount is on the higher end because then
the mindset is like hey look I just have
to test these like let's just move on
and and then having less emphasis on why
it worked, why it didn't work and so on.
And then sometimes there's a disconnect
because typically a company that is
testing 500 c creatives a month like
tend to have a team and usually there
are I don't want to call it silos but
you know the guy who is running the UA
is not doing the old briefs of the
creatives and then analyzing and then
giving the briefs and all that typically
in the smaller startups yes but in the
bigger teams there is that and then so
then the UI person's job is just to run
them and maybe analyze them if they
don't have the analyst team then to give
the creative let's say the optimization
manager to put them into briefs and get
the next production. So when the
quantity is so high like I think the
level of detail and sometimes also the
quality of analyzing and shaping the
next input is also being jeopardized a
bit because of the high quantity which
is not necessarily a win or something to
be proud of alone if your success rate
is low because also then the mindset
shifts like hey look I have 500
creatives I can't spend 5k on all of
them. Sometimes this gets into, oh, we
only spend $100 on these creatives and
that's it. Okay, but how did you decide
on that threshold? And I think finding
that threshold is such an important
thing for every account. For example,
there's no universal number that I would
give. It's very different from business
to business depending on your CPI,
depending on your other CPX metrics. But
what I would suggest is to look at your
cumulative spend and cumulative CPX
metrics, whether you're testing on a CPI
or cost per trial or just cost per
subscription and such, and see when they
stabilize. So, because I see a lot of
accounts with high spend, they're
sometimes just spending 10K, 20K only to
realize, oh, this is actually not a good
creative. I'm like, oh, really? I could
tell it after 500 bucks like look at the
data it was already bad like it was
already screaming like why did you spend
so much? So in order to avoid that
inefficiency and scaling it more
efficiently, you could easily look at
cumulative spend and cumulative
performance over time and to see where
your data stabilizes because we're not
going after the statistical significance
like no one has kind of money for that.
But we also don't want to spend just 20
30 bucks to see or we don't want to just
let the algorithm decide which one to
pick. So there the problem is the
following like just because algorithm
decides to deliver one creative over
others doesn't make the other creatives
bad creative. I think that's such a
misconception or interpreting in a I
would say in a wrong way. Like that
particular creative that got the 90% of
the spend was maybe lucky. We call it
like lucky 5,000 impressions because
Meta does some sort of a decision making
around first 5 to 10,000 uh impressions.
And if one of those 5,000 people who saw
the ad didn't engage or whatever it
signals that meta didn't receive, then
it will not deliver anymore, but it will
deliver the other one who just got maybe
one, two clicks and stuff like that. So,
and then I've seen that multiple times
where you take out that dominant ad from
that adset and all the other ads like
suddenly bloom and you're like, "Oh,
like they were also great ads, but
because of the other better ad or
however you want to call it and which is
not necessarily better ad as well
because sometimes meta call the shots
way too early. No conversions, nothing
like it doesn't even give a chance. So
in those cases, we don't call that
creative that got the all the spam
successful and all the rest bad
labeling. I think this is not universal
and this is really I think case by case
basis. I've also seen like adsets with
like 50 ads live. Oh, let's see what
algorithm likes and we will run it for a
week and then we will see what happens
and then what happens in that week 90%
goes to the same ad and because they
have this rules of thumb oh we run it
for 7 days and at certain I don't know
daily budget but then that's useless
when the 90% of the budget goes to one
creative like that's not a test like you
should in those cases for example break
the rules and like hey look this reached
my threshold this is my decision
threshold now I want to
uh what other ads going to perform for
that minimum threshold that you decide
based on your cumulative spend and
cumulative performance over time. Yeah.
So that's why like there is no one rule
that is valid for all. But I personally
try to get spend on the other creatives
if I see a dominant one. I believe that
every creative should have an equal
chance. So I democratize a bit within
the adset, right? And because I've seen
it countless times that the decision
that made by Meta was way too early.
Yes, we trust algorithms, but we want to
guide the algorithms. When we see a 80
90% of a dominant asset, let it be a
creative, let it be a country and such,
you're not fulfilling the potential of
the other variables. And I think this is
important. For example, if you put the
US with all the other smaller, let's say
European countries, there's a 90% chance
that at least 70% of the spend will go
to US because of its size and
everything. Also, you should never do
that anyway. Like you should always tear
by like CAC or LTV depending on what
you're optimizing towards and ideally
without those dominating variables. And
if there's a dominating one, then you
can always take it out, test it
separately, give a chance to the rest
because it's not meaningful to have, I
don't know, let's say like just a couple
of thousand dollars spent with a really
good CAC, really good ROS. Well, if you
cannot scale that and then you try to
scale by increasing that existing
campaign's budget, but that country that
you want to actually scale is not
increasing its spend necessarily because
if it's getting dominated by the other
bigger countries or based on whatever
logic that depending on your setup. So
in those cases then yes you can
experiment with the value based the
rules and stuff like that and that we
can talk about later in the testing and
and the learning side of things.
>> What's the tactical move then there when
you do have that you know quote unquote
winning creative that's getting 90% of
the spend. Is it better to pull the
other creatives out because that ad set
already knows how to target that
specific ad to the right people, to the
right geography and everything else. Is
it better to pull the quote unperforming
ads and give them a shot somewhere else
or is it better to pull the performing
ad into a a different set? What's what's
the best way to to actually implement
that? depends on whether this creative
is in a creative test adset versus in a
BAU adset. If it's in a BAU adset, then
I I would create another BAU adset and
then I would include those creatives
that were under delivering into the new
one and I wouldn't touch that something
that is working well. But if it is
within the creative testing adset and if
it already reached my threshold then I
would already pause it and then I would
put it on the bench to get ready to
upload to BAU adsets whenever the team
will do the creative refresh. So it is
case by case basis but in general rule
of thumb is don't touch something is
working well but depends on what case we
are talking about.
Yeah. Yeah, that makes sense. I did want
to step back and uh not to put words in
Eric's mouth, maybe his point is more to
not overly focus on a single hypothesis
for why a creative one. So, like going
back to the whole like, you know, should
you learn from creatives? Because I I do
want to dig a little deeper into kind of
how you think about what you can learn.
Um, and the example he used was you look
at a creative that has a dog in it and
you're like, "Oh, like people love
dogs." And so that's why the creative
one and you maybe get overly focused and
then to your point, then you go create
200 new assets all with dogs. But maybe
it wasn't the dog. Maybe it was just
that it was a something cute and a cat
one would perform just as well or a
panda one would perform even better or
ocelot or like who even knows, right?
How do you think about forming a
hypothesis around that? Because it seems
like that that's really the important
step is is like not being overly
confident in why you think something
won, but instead just allowing it to
help you form a hypothesis for other
things to test based on why a multitude
of reasons why that creative could have
won.
>> Yeah. I mean, you should never just
produce 200 variations of just from a
one signal. I think it's always in in
phases. So let's let's take the dog
example. Okay, let's have the same dog.
Let's have a puppy. Let's have another
breed. Let's have another animal. So
just to test and see if it's the animal
or not. So what we want to understand is
what makes the difference. Is it the
dog? Is it an animal? Is it something
else? And once we figured it out, then
we would slowly roll out the production
and so on. So it's never about oh the
dog won now we need 200 variations of
the dog. It's more about okay like is it
the dog? We want to validate that. So in
every step we want to do that and we
want to do in both directions. That's
why we have both iterative concepts and
the radical concepts. Iterative would be
oh let's put another breed let's put two
dogs maybe it's even more effective and
uh but you know the in the radical one
you can have completely different
hypothesis than what doesn't work based
on what works today. but also on based
on other sources. So like when it comes
to what creative to test, I think you
should utilize both the first party data
and the third party data. It's not
always about the first party data. So
first party data meaning like your meta
creative output. That's one variable
that then that's a valid let's say
input. But you also have let's say for
particular copy like or let's say if
you're testing particular let's say
visuals and such that also exists in
your app right okay what what is the
most popular thing in the app that is
more valuable for the users you know you
basically look at within your data set
like you look at your within your inapp
analytics uh what you can learn what
resonates with users you look at your
high LTV users like why do they stick
around what do they use the most what
messaging resonates with them and then
because our goal in performance
marketing is to find more of those high
LTV users. So testing like test results
from test campaigns is one variable but
inapp analytics data is another data
input that we can utilize. And then we
have the third party data where we have
competitor concepts. What works for
competitors? We have overall trending
memes or concepts or audios and such.
And then you could have category level
concepts. They're not really direct
competitor concepts, but other big
players that are doing well within your
category. What are they doing? What do
how do they advertise their product? So
what you can learn from them? So then
you bring and merge all these data sets
together. Then you decide on okay, you
know what? Of course you give a lot more
weight to the meta test results. But it
is not a 100% hey this is it guys, dogs,
let's go. So it is about merging that.
So when you hyperlise the next
iterations,
it's also should come from what worked
and what didn't work. Not only for you
but also for others. You can check the
meta library to see how long competitors
are running a particular ad and how many
variations of that. If there is one
concept with 15 variations and that is a
particular the only one that has 15
variations compared other ones having
just two and three, you should be able
to interpret that likely that creative
performing well for them. That's why
they're exploring more angles. So it is
important to analyze and put enough
resources and attention to the planning
part of the experiment. Exactly. because
of this way and not just act like I
don't know growth bro and hey this
worked well let's do 200 of them and so
on so I think this balanced effort
planning and executing matters here
>> how do you think about analyzing
competitor ads though because to your
earlier point there's a lot of people
out there just following the playbook
and and creating 15 variations because
they formed a bad hypothesis around so
how do you actually dig into these
competitor ads and try and figure out
like if it is actually working for them.
And that's something I just see
throughout the whole industry broadly is
that it's too easy to overindex on
something you observe without the data
and say, "Oh, this must be working.
These 15 creatives must be working
because they've created 15 variations."
That may have been like a dumb move and
you just don't realize how poorly it's
performing and they don't even realize
how poorly it's performing because they
don't have it instrumented well. They're
not tracking deeper in the funnel. So
like how do you think about looking at
competitor data and getting any insights
from that when you when you don't have
the full picture of why, how, what their
process is, how good their stuff is
instrumented, how smart their people
are, etc., etc.
>> Yeah. So anything you see online let's
say should be only as inspiration and
not treated as this because I've also
seen and heard people saying we tried it
it didn't work but I don't know leather
is using it like so then they justify
and then they defend oh but it worked
for them like so as you said like it
doesn't mean anything for the brand
exactly because of the reasons that you
mentioned so it should be just treated
as inspiration as another input that's
why I talk about a pool of inputs that
will shape together the next iterations.
It is never about oh let's copy one to
one whatever compare is doing. Oh let's
copy this trend. It comes down to how I
can customize this to my own personas
and in my own ways based on what worked
for me before and what didn't work for
me before. So at the end this needs to
all go in that processing machine that
considers the personas the past
performance the current performance and
all your learnings and then you test it.
So it's never about oh competitor is
doing this great let's do the same. I
think that is probably why many people
are getting upset I don't know when they
just copy the same pay wall or same
creative and then finding out oh it
doesn't work for us. Well why should it
work? uh it's different audience,
different funnel, different pricing,
different messaging, different promises.
So although for example on the web
funnels like many of them look very
alike especially in the health and
fitness space for many years and then
everyone copies from each other. So like
pretty much a lot of the health and
fitness web funnels are similar now.
Some are missing of course some I don't
know smaller elements here and there but
the conceptually like they're the same.
At the end of the day, you should just
run to see. So they should be treated as
inspiration and as a variant in your
whole test hypothesis and not as a test
hypothesis itself.
>> Yeah. And and then one other kind of
elephant in the room in all of this is
making sure that you're actually
instrumenting things well and actually
testing well and can actually interpret
the results properly. Bah recently had a
tweet that I thought was was amusingly
provocative. He said, I won't quote it
exactly, but it was something along the
lines of like half the people who say
the Blinkist payw wall works for them
just aren't testing it properly.
[laughter]
So, how do you think about like in all
of this experimentation and forming
hypothesis and like running all these
tests, how do you think about like even
just validating your own process and
testing and tooling and and that side of
things to make sure you're even drawing
the right conclusions from the data?
>> Yeah, I mean that's also I think what we
covered earlier like 50% of the issue
with something working or not is about
how they test it. So I can like totally
get like why he mentions that because I
hear like similar stories. They're like,
"Oh, we tested XY Z pricing because
competitor is the same, but our
conversion rate dropped and our revenue
dropped." Like you shouldn't take these
kind of stuff as the hard truth or your
strategy. It should be only as a variant
and as a a source of inspiration. And in
terms of how to interpret the results
like everyone has their own inapp
analytics tool or their third party tool
depending on what test are we talking
about. If you're talking about let's say
the payw wall tests and stuff like inapp
analytics is the way to go. If you're
talking about creative tests and so on
then we are talking about MMP as a a
source of truth relatively speaking
here. But if you're talking about
incremental impact of a channel, like
we're not looking at the last click
obviously. So that's also one thing that
there is not one single source of truth
for every answer you're looking for. So
if you want to compare creatives against
each other, like MMP could be your best
friend. But if you want to compare the
impact of UAC versus Meta, MMP is likely
not your best friend because one is a
push channel, one is a pull channel but
and the competitiveness of the vertical
and such but typically UAC is a lot
cheaper because of the search and which
of those higher proportion of those
searches also coming from the brand
search and so on. So you wouldn't do a
budgeting decision or forecast just
based on um MMP and such. So you might
want to rely on incrementality and mm
and conducting experiments around the
geo lift and the hold out and the and
the blackout test and so on to come to
such conclusions. Knowing your baseline,
knowing your seasonality problems get
different at different stages. like you
don't have to worry about incrementality
when you're just spending 100k a month.
I think it might matter but it matters a
lot more once you get bigger because a
lot of the decisions at such stage are
driven by MMP/ lastclick which is normal
because when you are at that stage you
don't have all the data infrastructure
set up to measure incrementality and and
and so on like I'm maybe generalizing a
bit but typical startup don't have all
those kind of tools inhouse or third
party like to make it happen and once to
get to certain level I would say 500k
plus then these are becoming more a lot
more important and prominent in
decisions because then you start with
the yearly budgets and then the
forecasts and everything and the
profitability starts mattering a lot
more than before and so on depending on
let's say your investor vision as well
at the end of the day you should just
stick to one tool for certain decisions
While you should also cross check with
other tooling time to time just as a
baseline. I'm not saying for example you
should use app store connect as your
baseline. No. But if your MMP and meta
are very different but your app store
connect CPP data and meta matches that
should give you also some like signals.
take it as there are source of truth
that you should be sticking to but don't
take them blindly as this is it like UAC
is the best channel let's double the
budget only to see potentially the
impact is output is not the double and
so on so that's why then it comes down
to multiple tools and multiple ways of
interpreting it for example
incrementality and last click also
conflicts or mm um might be conflicting
with day-to-day decisions as well
depending on at what level you do MM or
at what cadence you feed the MM and how
you calibrate it. Having worked on so
many different apps and audited so many
different accounts over the years, do
you have any horror stories of like the
data teams SQL was wrong and and for a
year they were just like making really
bad decisions or or the MMP was not
hooked up correctly or like do you have
any like just crazy horror stories from
all these accounts that you've worked
with or multiple crazy horror stories of
uh just making bad decisions because the
process wasn't set up.
>> Yeah, I think story was something like
this. They switched the MMP and then
they didn't implement the events on the
new MMP. I think there are probably
plenty, but there are also some must
avoid at all cost type of things such as
I remember one project switched MMPs and
they contacted me after a month and
saying like, "Hi, we need some help. We
cannot figure out what's happening." And
the issue was so obvious. So they
switched MMPs. They didn't implement any
events on the new MMP and the old MMP
was still connected to meta. They still
had campaigns optimizing on meta. And
this is like a sizable company. But the
problem is they have a different team
handling everything MMP. They have a
different team
>> handling meta only kind of a silos and
stuff. And I was like, "How did you not
realize this for almost a month?"
They're like, "Yeah, because it's not
our thing." And so on. So this stuff is
like I think on a very extreme level.
Other than that, I don't know. I've seen
as crazy as someone spend 100k on a
creative with 100 plus dollars and did
not stop it before. I think it was like
90k something. Didn't stop. Like I was
like, really?
>> With a $100 cost per install.
>> Yeah.
>> Wo.
>> Relatively. It was not the crazy high
compared to other ones, but it was high
enough that you should have killed it
after $2,000 max and not wait for
100,000.
>> But so that happens like when I mean
it's not an excuse, but it tend to
happen in large accounts with no
automation guard rails. Yeah, let's keep
it this way. like no no guard rails in
place and you're just really focused on
execution and day-to-day business and
you're missing out on hygiene checks,
rules of thumb and all that kind of
stuff because you're too focused on
testing the maximum amount of creatives
and so on. So
>> maybe maybe this is another good rule of
thumb to come out of this podcast about
not following the rules of thumb, but I
I don't know how you would divide it up,
but maybe 80% of your growth teams
efforts should be focused on testing and
moving fast and all that stuff, but you
want to leave like 10 or 20% to like be
continually auditing your processes,
continually auditing your data
structures, continuing to audit your
events structures and and all of those
processes that are in place to make sure
that that you don't end up in those kind
of situations.
>> Yeah. Like another example I just uh
remembered is on the positive side of
things. We were doing creative testing
and and then we did find the winner at
the end thanks to interpreting the
output and iterating on those output. So
it actually uh works when you like do
the iteration and and find more winners.
And we were able to I think 5x the
campaign budget within like two weeks
with the same and even decreasing like
cost per purchase and we were not
applying 20% increase per day. If you
see that your daily budget is 2K but
Algo spends 3K and you get the same
performance. I was like, let me handle
the bid and budget for this campaign
because I see something I see something
very unusual and I was so excited about
it that we literally went hockey stick
and the cost purchase literally on a
downhill and that's like any UA
manager's dream and in those cases like
but also the budget at some point was
spending the double of the daily budget
but it is no problem as long as you have
the performance and talking about as a
problem like there are also companies
who put let's say overspend on a Sunday
as a problem but then again it's just a
fact the my approach is okay what do you
do for it have you decreased the bids
and the budgets like how did you try to
overcome this code problem and then
they're like oh like it's just the algo
decides on that I'm like yeah but you
can guide the algo if you put a lower
budget if you have some automation in
place then algo be like okay like I
don't they don't want me to spend more
and so on and there are multiple ways to
control it in a way. You cannot control
it 100% of course but we can guide the
algorithms in that way. Like another
example is the the cap inflated budget
strategy where we have a million dollars
a day budget at the campaign level and
which is not a good advice unless you
put a campaign spend limits in place.
Right? So, as long as you have the guard
rails in, you won't be spending 1
million a day. Of course, uh you will
only spend up to your total campaign
cap. And we tested this to bypass the
pacing function, although we were still
using the bit caps and the cost caps.
And this was like earlier this year when
we tested it. And it was also
recommended by Meta. And basically it
did work quite well because we were able
to capture a lot more higher quality
traffic. We did not spend a million
dollar a day. The spend varied across
the days, but we were still able to get
a stable performance with such a crazy
budget that the algorithm is not pacing
the day anymore because it is very
large, right? Because the way the daily
budget works, it divides the budget to
24 hours in a way that of course it
doesn't it never does it equally in a
way. You know, you always have this kind
of fluctuations. the evening times it
peaks up and so on. But by putting a
million a day again always with the
budget caps and spending limits at every
level. So
>> yeah, this this [laughter] is one that
could get really dangerous.
>> Yeah.
>> So I think if I'm understanding this
correct, is it at the creative or that
the daily budget would be at the entire
account level? Is that where you're
setting the daily budget or at the
campaign?
>> Okay, at the campaign level. So you set
the campaign level budget to a million
and the reason you do that is that
Facebook or Meta Meta will try and
throttle your performance to not
overspend in the morning. So so let's
say if you're let's say instead your
budget was 100K and 100K is what you
actually wanted to spend for the day.
And the problem would be that Meta's
like oo they only want to spend 100K. we
shouldn't serve too many ads this
morning because we know the night's
going to pick up and so we're going to
like kind of throttle the morning ad
delivery. So what you're saying is like
at the campaign level you set that to a
million but then you very carefully go
through each bid set and set caps there.
But then how do you balance those bid
caps so you still don't end up spending
or or maybe you want to give it some
freedom to maybe spend 200k or 300k or
like Yeah. So then how do you dial in
those bid caps where it does still allow
the algorithm a little more flexibility
in in more aggressively spending?
>> Yeah. So of course you start
conservatively, right? Like uh if you're
cost per purchases 50, you want to start
I don't know around 45 and so like or
10% 10 to 20% below and you might not
get delivery. Then you play it slowly.
And by the way, this is not for let's
say the not for beginners like
[laughter]
>> so why I'm saying that because this
works well at large accounts with large
learnings that they are spending 50k a
day anyway type of a thing and they want
to see if they can spend more than 50k a
day if they can spend 100k a day and
this is one of the ways to unlock that
and again with the campaign limits. So
for example, how do you ensure that you
you don't spend 200k but you want to
spend only 50k? You set a campaign uh
spend limit and then you put a 50k as a
you say like regardless of how good is
my performance I don't want to spend
more than 50k. So you put that 50k but
that 50k is not stopping your auction
dynamics because auction dynamics are
based on the bids and the budget and the
cap is like as far as I know it is
another control mechanism that is not
going into the whole auction in terms of
pacing and the bidding and and and all
that stuff. So it's just a guard rail.
So that's the way you control it. So you
have the bid as a control mechanism and
then you have the safety mechanism by
setting up a max limit and then you want
to spend another 50k. You're happy with
the first 50k then you increase your
campaign limit to 100k then you give
that room again and then now you want to
spend more so you increase it. So
basically you are still in control
you're just bypassing the auction
dynamics in in in this way as an
example. So and we tried this for
multiple accounts and we had some great
results. It didn't work for also some
they didn't get delivery or when they
get delivery it was too quick too much
and then they had to start at like a 10k
and 20k and so on per day and so on. I
don't know what happened later. I know
the cases that it worked and then the
cases that didn't work I didn't follow
up on the latest status because I'm also
busy with my full-time job. But yeah
like there are many this kind of things
you can test and this is of course one
extreme. You should not test stuff only
for sake of extreme testing but there
are simple stuff as like the valuebased
rules. You can test those bit modifiers
that exist forever but now it used to be
available only through FMPs. Now it's
available within the UI. like if you
have performance difference above 20 30%
among the let's say the placements or
demographics and such it is worth
testing it and and yeah so there are a
lot of tests to do across all channels.
So when you want to look for room for
growth like you should look at both
vertically and horizontally. So
horizontally will be like at the channel
level okay are we really maxing out at
every channel? Do we do I have the
response curves of all the channels? Can
I really double on this channel or
rather spend x% on this channel and y%
on another channel channel? This usually
will come from the MM output because MM
will consider all your various sources
of data although mostly it's looking at
the impression span and conversions and
such but it does know the seasonality
because you upload your last 24 months
data and such. And then when I talk
about the vertical side it is about I
don't know on meta I gave already like a
few examples on we talked about the
audience testing we talked about like
clustering based on CAC or LTV depending
on how you optimize we talked about the
value based like there are like 50 plus
I think tests that you can do but the
prioritization of this test should come
from your current data and then on UAC
like it should start as basic as okay
what are you bidding on are you bidding
on Firebase events or your MMP events.
Are you still optimizing towards an
install or are you optimizing towards a
lowerfunnel? And have you tested
excluding your brand keyword? You know,
what is incremental value? So at the
different stages so starting from so I
think we talk a lot about the recent
examples were more about like large
advertisers with large budgets where
they can invest into in-house teams to
build all this mm or get a third party
tool to basically utilize the outsource
the mm but at a small scale you can also
just turn on and off like large
advertisers cannot afford to do that but
if you're a smaller advertiser like if
you're just spending Okay, I don't want
to uh number now because I said small
advertiser. Let's say if you can afford
to turn off the channel regardless of
your size. Let's put it this way. If you
can afford uh just do it. If you cannot
afford then you have to use these kind
of either the geo lift or the blackout
or all that or there are tons of
scientific statistical studies you can
run for the sake of incrementality and
such. But the most basic one is
sometimes switch on and off and then and
observe the outcome. And again there are
no one right way to do things. It really
depends on your size. It really depends
on your market vertical and such. So I
know some of our folks within our
industry like they have great advice
that are applicable to most accounts but
they're not applicable to every single
account as well. So that's why I
mentioned at the beginning of the talk
like take them as inspiration. Take them
as like like if you hear something this
didn't work at all be like great I will
try it but later but don't be like oh we
should not even try that unless you have
also evidence that it will also not work
for you or there are the cues because at
the end of the day we have to prioritize
how many things we can test and yes
there are 100 things to test. Yes it's
good to utilize someone else's
experience instead of you finding out by
yourself. It's good to leverage other
people's learnings and that's definitely
a a good point. But what I'm just saying
is like just don't take it as like don't
take out that test from your road map
because someone said it didn't work for
them was my kind of main message here.
Yeah, this is a really fun I I feel like
this was also a fun contrast even or not
a contrast but a complement to the
signal engineering discussion in that
Thomas talked about and you know the
industry's been talking more about about
signal engineering as a way to kind of
manipulate the algorithms if you will to
to coach the algorithms to influence the
algorithms and then so many things that
you talked about today are also ways
especially that those last few comments
around the you manipulating big caps and
things like that like the point is
there's there's so many ways to tinker
and tinkering with bids and caps and all
those kind of things and and maybe for
some like focus on your creative, let
the algorithms do their thing and you
you get enough performance and you don't
need a big team and like whatever it
works. And again, that's kind of your
point, right? It's like don't feel like
you need to test all of this. Don't feel
like you need to try the bid cap, but at
some point maybe you do need to scale
and you're hitting a wall. There's a
hundred different things you can try to
break through that wall. And I think
you've shared a lot of really fun kind
of contrarian or just maybe less talked
about tactics to help break through
those walls when you are struggling.
When you've done the test and realize
you do actually have a problem, it's not
just a fact of the business and that
there really is a problem. There's like
so many different ways to tackle it and
just try crazy stuff. So, it's been a
super fun conversation.
>> Yeah. I mean I also want to add one more
thing to what I said in terms of the the
testing like sometimes people hear
something and they're like oh like we
heard I don't know someone said mapping
trial to purchase works better like oh
should we also do that I'm
[clears throat] like what is your reason
what is your like diagnosis on like how
did you come up with that hypothesis and
like why would you change stuff so
that's why also like there's a
misconception on oh let's just test
everything. But that also sometimes
contradicts with don't touch if
something is working well. And the
particular example I'm talking about is
event mapping for example because you
mentioned also signal engineering and
stuff. It's also at the basic level like
sometimes you don't need to come up with
specific demographics triggered events.
Sometimes it's also about optimizing
what event you map on meta side. for
example sometimes. So there are
typically three options I see people do.
They either map their trial to trial,
they map their trial to purchase or they
map their trial to subscribe to give
better signal to the algorithm and some
people just do it purchase because
everyone does it. So it is great as long
as it works for you. If you're happy, if
you're profitable, if you've been using
it for 5 years, if you scaled like don't
touch it. Don't try to change it because
your whole earnings is based on that. On
the other side, if you're not happy with
the purchase optimization because your
cost per purchase is almost higher than
your LTV and then if you're not running
the account because of that, then it's
time to calibrate slash try something
else. And of course, this should not be
the main thing to look at. You should
first analyze the account to understand
why things didn't work and what. And one
of the levers also could be on the event
mapping/ the signal engineering side of
things because when you optimize towards
a purchase where the meta has a lot of
information on and which is great
because it goes after people who
actually purchases things. But also you
should think about okay these people are
purchasing anything. Just because
someone bought a skirt doesn't mean that
they're gonna try your app. You know,
there's also a bit of the relevancy
there. So I remember like I think it was
sometime last year had an app that had a
really high CAC and they because they
mapped their trial to purchase and then
all we did was mapping their trial event
to trial and their cost per purchase/
the actual cost per trial went down by I
think around 35%. only with that change.
Same creatives, same campaigns, just
different event optimization. Also,
their CPMs changed as well because if
everyone is optimizing towards a
purchase, so and then the guy is, let's
say, this brand is optimizing towards
purchase because his AOV is $200. He's
willing to pay up to, let's assume $200
versus a cost per trials worth for your
business is $15, let's say, or $10. How
are you going to compete with the guy
who is willing to pay 200 from the
auction dynamics point of view? That guy
is spending more and the way to give the
auto bid a signal is you increase your
budget. You indirectly increase your bid
when you have the auto bid when you
don't have the bid cap and cost cap. And
then that guy keeps increasing and then
you're just getting crushed and he's
maybe getting the highest intent and
you're getting the lowest intent
purchasers and stuff like that. So
there's a mismatch on like what you want
to get and what you tell the algorithm.
And then on the other side when you map
your trial to trial, you're honest about
your kind of intentions and the app
because the only way for algorithm to
know your business are the events you're
sending to your events manager to your
meta events manager. So also the events
that you map should also logically make
sense and should ideally have a funnel
logic as well that I've seen the other
day someone mapped subscription
cancellation to add to cart trial
converted to something else and there is
a subscribe event purchase event there's
everything. So for meta like what is
this? Is this a ecom shop? Is this a
subscription app? Is this whatever? And
all these advertising businesses that
are worth billions are built on machine
learning because machine learns from all
the signals. And if you send this kind
of wrong signals that doesn't make a
funnel and then the algorithms are
calibrating the whole auction dynamics
because they're optimizing their own
eCPMs with likelihood to convert based
on your typical funnel and typical
behavior. Like these are like my
personal opinion but I'm just
interpreting a story here. Like
algorithm is not confident to show that
advertiser's ad to that user because
there is much clearer signal on another
advertiser's funnel based on this user's
historic activity that is known to meta.
He the meta algo will rather show
advertisers B's ad to the that user and
not A because he doesn't know if this
user will convert or not. And he knows
that if this user will not convert on
the advertiser's A's ad, he will not
increase his budget. And Meta optimizes
towards the spend/ the advertiser value,
right? So, and for meta to work at
optimal level, signal engineering is one
thing like to improve what you're
sending, but fundamentally you should
not send mixed signals for the sake of
what you're potentially thinking as
signal engineering as well. So in
general keep it simple, keep it logical.
Don't send all possible events because
you can. I think that's what also people
do. Oh like why don't we track also this
because look we can send this event.
It's difficult to quantify what I just
said, but it is just talking to Facebook
product managers like knowing how this
platform learns from the data, learns
from the signal and so on. Like this is
my interpretation of that and I see that
the simpler accounts also do better
because of that, right? Like it used to
be different like you had 50 types of
campaigns and so on. Now like you have
the broad interest and the lookalike
that is all you need. Uh, of course
there are more, but I'm just simplifying
past versus now because algos know
exactly whom to go after based on the
signals that it gets and based on the
signals that it has on the user. So the
signals that your app has is if it's
totally different than what users engage
with all the other apps and all the
other businesses, then there's a
mismatch, right? And that's a whole
business model of meta. It will find
exactly the user. It learns from the
users that it showed impression to. It
gets the conversion as a feedback and
then it will try to find more similar
people. So when you send this mixed
signals mixed funnel that doesn't make
sense from the auction calculation point
of view then you're also potentially
losing out on this kind of
opportunities. So having said that like
if you're happy with your current event
mapping don't try to just challenge it
for the sake of challenging. If you are
unhappy and thinking there is a room to
try something different, I would suggest
create another event that gets triggered
at the same place. For example, the
trial start. Add another trial start
event in your MMP. Then map that to
let's say to subscribe. Then run a split
test purchase versus subscribe to see
like which event is more resonating. Of
course, like the history of each will
not be the same. So I would at least
wait a week or two so that the events
manager will build some history and
understand what does this event mean for
their algo and so on. Again it's
difficult to quantify wait one week
versus 2 weeks but it's just to build
some data history and then run the test
and then see how it is. And that's
exactly what we did for this particular
project and then we saw a 35%
improvement just like that. So sometimes
you shouldn't think too complex on okay
but maybe they also come back on day
three then I will fire this super high
LTV in predictor event that you can also
do that but also just step back zoom out
okay what am I telling the algorithm how
does algorithm know me like is algorithm
XY Z so it should start at this basic
level and so on
>> yeah which was to your broader point
that there's so many things to play with
but don't break things just because
people say you should try and break them
like form a hypothesis for why this
would perform better and then
systematically test it versus assuming
because everybody said signal
engineering is going to work that you
should be doing that exact form of
signal engineering. So yeah, it's been
so fun chatting through all of this.
Anything you wanted to share as you wrap
up? I know you do take on contracting
work, but you're also working on your
own app studio if people did want to get
in touch or are you taking clients or
anything like that? Thank you also for
your insights and always happy to help
happy to chat when it comes to like Mart
when it comes to UA challenges when it
comes to attribution CRO ASO like that's
what I've been dealing daily for the
past 12 years because of my main project
and always happy to chat always happy to
learn from you as well and uh learn from
the community so that's how we all grow
>> what what's the best place to reach out
uh just LinkedIn or what's the best
place get in touch with you.
>> Yeah, LinkedIn would be
>> cool. All right. Well, such a fun
conversation. I really appreciate you
joining me.
>> Yeah. Thank you. Thank you so much.
>> Awesome. [music]
>> Thanks so much for listening. If you
have a minute, please leave a review in
your favorite podcast player. You can
also stop by chat.subclub.com
to join our private community.
[music]